Irwin Hasen Cartoons
Irwin Hasen Cartoons
1955-1968
Hasen, Irwin, 1918-2015.
21 linear ft.
Over 3,500 pieces of original artwork for the comic strip Dondi and five proofs.
149040
Biographical History
Irwin Hasen (1918- ) is an American cartoonist and comic book artist.
Hasen was born in New York City on July 8, 1918 and graduated from Dewitt Clinton High School. He studied at the National Academy of Design and the Art Students League. Initially, Hasen pursued sports cartooning, drawing boxing-related caricatures. He was drafted during World War II and was the editor of the Fort Dix Gazette until his discharge in 1946.
Hasen had worked as a freelance advertising artist but expanded into comic books in the late 1930s. His credits during the 1940s and 1950s include work with Archie Publications; Detective Comics, romance comics for Fawcett; DC Comics titles including Green Lantern and Wild Cat; the Flash at DC Comics and work for Bert Whitman Associates. From 1944 to 1945 Hasen drew the Goldbergs strip which was distributed by the New York Post Syndicate. Hasen also produced promotional comics for Bazooka Bubble Gum.
Hasen became an active member of the National Cartoonists Society and while on an NCS sponsored tour of Germany, he met Gus Edson. Together they created the Dondi comic strip, about a World War II orphan, with Hasen drawing the strip and Edson writing the story. The Chicago Tribune-New York News syndicate distributed the strip to over 100 newspapers from 1955 to 1986 and Dondi was also adapted into a motion picture.
The National Cartoonists Society has recognized Hasen's work with several awards including the best newspaper story strip for Dondi in 1961 and 1962 and a Silver T-Square Award in 1969. At the 1999 San Diego Comicon, Hasen received the Inkpot Award.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Irwin Hasen Cartoons are arranged into a single series.
Dondi (1955-1968) contains approximately 3,553 pieces of original artwork for the comic strip of the same name as well as five proofs. There are 3,022 daily strips and 531 Sunday strips. Please note for several days there are both Sunday and daily formats. Also of interest is one Sunday strip produced in color (September 30, 1956).
All are signed "Edson and Hasen" although Hasen is typically credited with drawing the strip while Edson wrote the strip. The strips were drawn in pen and ink on illustration board. Notations appear in pencil and blue pencil. Each work contains a copyright notice sticker. Many strips feature detailed sketches on the back. Frequently, Sunday panels were completed in pieces and then pasted onto a larger piece of illustration board comprising the final Sunday version of the comic strip. On some pieces, the date and title of the strip have been stamped. Artwork for daily strips measures approximately 7" x 22". Dimensions for Sunday artwork varies between 16 3/4" x 23 3/4" and 20 ½" x 29".
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged chronologically. Daily and weekly (Sunday) strips are housed separately.
Related Material
For additional Dondi material, see the
Gus Edson Papers
.
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Hasen, Irwin, 1918-2015.; Tribune Company.; Chicago Tribune Syndicate.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Orphans -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Children -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Dondi (comic strip); Cartoons (humorous images); Proofs (printed matter); Comic strips.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Irwin Hasen, 1967-1968.
Inventory
- Dondi cartoons, Click here for a detailed inventory.
  - Daily cartoons, 3,022 items
    - Daily cartoons, 1955 Dec-1956 Dec (Oversize 1)
    - Daily cartoons, 1957 Jan-1958 Jun (Oversize 2)
    - Daily cartoons, 1958 Jul-1959 Mar (Oversize 3)
    - Daily cartoons, 1959 Apr-Sep (Oversize 4)
    - Daily cartoons, 1959 Nov-1960 Jun (Oversize 5)
    - Daily cartoons, 1960 Jul-1961 May (Oversize 6)
    - Daily cartoons, 1961 Jun-Dec (Oversize 7)
    - Daily cartoons, 1962 Jan-Aug (Oversize 8)
    - Daily cartoons, 1962 Sep-1963 Apr (Oversize 9)
    - Daily cartoons, 1963 May-Nov (Oversize 10)
    - Daily cartoons, 1963 Dec-1964 Jun (Oversize 11)
    - Daily cartoons, 1964 Jul-1965 Feb (Oversize 12)
    - Daily cartoons, 1965 Mar-Aug (Oversize 13)
    - Daily cartoons, 1965 Sep-1966 Mar (Oversize 14)
    - Daily cartoons, 1966 Apr-Sep (Oversize 15)
    - Daily cartoons, 1966 Oct-1967 (Oversize 16)
    - Daily cartoons, 1967 (Oversize 17)
    - Daily cartoons, 1967-1968 Apr (Oversize 18)
  - Sunday cartoons, 531 items
    - Sunday cartoons, 1955 Oct (Oversize 19)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1955 Dec-1956 Sep (Oversize 30)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1956 Oct-1957 Mar (Oversize 19)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1957 Apr-1958 Aug (Oversize 20)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1958 Sep-1959 Dec (Oversize 21)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1960 (Oversize 22)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1961-1962 (Oversize 23)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1962 Jun-1963 Apr (Oversize 24)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1963 May-Dec (Oversize 25)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1964 (Oversize 26)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1965 (Oversize 27)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1966 (Oversize 28)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1967-1968 (Oversize 29)